Allen Townsend Terrell
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Allen Townsend Terrell papers
1908-1982
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Terrell, Allen Townsend
4.5 linear feet
The papers of New York, Rome, and Paris painter Allen Townsend Terrell painter measure 4.5 linear feet and date from 1908-1982. Included are biographical materials; detailed letters from Terrell to his parents; fourteen diaries describing European travels; scattered financial records; three sketchbooks and miscellaneous sketches; printed material; and photographs of Terrell, his colleagues, his home and studios, artwork, and exhibition installations.
Provenance
Allen Townsend Terrell donated his papers in 7 installments between 1975 and 1981.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Allen Townsend Terrell (1897-1986) was a painter and sculptor who worked in Paris, Rome, and New York. Terrell was born in Riverhead, New York and graduated from the Columbia University School of Architecture in 1921. He also studied painting and sculpture at the Art Students League with Edward McCartan and at the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts with Albert Laessle. In 1924, he studied in France at the Conservatoire Américain de Fontainebleau with sculptor Charles Despiau, and at the Académie Julian in Paris.
Between 1924 and 1926, Terrell established a studio in Paris, later moving to Rome between 1928 and 1931. From 1934 to 1935, he taught watercolor and still life painting at the Parsons School of Design.
Among other exhibitions in Paris, New York, and Philadelphia, Terrell had a solo exhibition at the National Arts Club in 1975. He was a member of the American Watercolor Society and president of the Alumni of the American School at Fontainebleau.
Allen Townsend Terrell died on July 8, 1986.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of New York, Rome, and Paris painter Allen Townsend Terrell painter measure 4.5 linear feet and date from 1908-1982. Included are biographical materials; detailed letters from Terrell to his parents; fourteen diaries describing European travels; scattered financial records; three sketchbooks and miscellaneous sketches; printed material; and photographs of Terrell, his colleagues, his home and studios, artwork, and exhibition installations.
Biographical material includes a passport, membership cards for miscellaneous organizations, brief biographical accounts, and a guestbook containing signatures from several exhibition openings. There are almost daily letters written by Terrell to his parents describing his travels and education in the arts while in Europe. Scattered letters are from friends and colleagues, including one from Albert Laessle.
Fourteen diaries describe daily events in Terell's European travels. Scattered financial material includes banking records and miscellaneous receipts.
Three sketchbooks contain several block prints and miscellaneous sketches by Terrell. Printed material includes clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs for Terrell and for others, as well as programs, and miscellaneous brochures. Photographs are of Terrell, and of his colleagues, studio, and artwork, in addition to albums containing photographs of his apartment, the Riverhead studio, commissioned projects, and exhibition installations.
Arrangement
The collection is organized as 7 series; each series is arranged chronologically.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1924-1978 (Boxes 1, 6; 3 folders)
Series 2: Letters, 1908-1978 (Boxes 1-3; 2.8 linear feet)
Series 3: Diaries, 1965-1978 (Boxes 3-4; 12 folders)
Series 4: Financial Material, 1925-1933 (Box 4; 7 folders)
Series 5: Artwork, 1925-1982 (Boxes 4, 6; 7 folders)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1911-1976 (Box 4; 15 folders)
Series 7: Photographs, 1925-1972 (Box 5; 15 folders)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the catalog under the following terms:
Subjects-Topical:
Painters; Travel -- Europe; Artists' studios -- Photographs; Art -- Study and teaching -- France -- Paris; Art -- Study and teaching -- Italy
Types of Materials:
Photographs; Travel diaries; Sketches; Sketchbooks
Names:
Laessle, Albert, 1877-1954
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1924-1978, Series 1:; (Boxes 1, 6; 3 folders)
  Biographical Material includes a passport, membership cards for miscellaneous organizations including the Art Students League, and brief biographical accounts. There is also a small number of miscellaneous notes including a guestbook containing signatures from several exhibition openings.
  - Passport, Membership Cards, and Biographical Accounts, 1924-1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, 1944-1966, undated, (see also Box 6) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Oversized Guestbook, 1944-1953 (Box 6 (sol))
- Letters, 1908-1978, Series 2:; (Boxes 1-3; 2.8 linear feet)
  Almost daily letters were written by Terrell to his parents describing his travel and education during the years that he studied art and worked in Paris and Rome. Abbreviated transcripts of these letters were written by Terrell later in his life. General letters are from friends and colleagues including one letter from Terrell's professor Albert Laessle.
  - Abbreviated Transcripts of Letters Dated 1918-1923 from Terrell, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Abbreviated Transcripts of Letters Dated 1924 from Terrell, 1978, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
  - Abbreviated Transcripts of Letters Dated 1925 from Terrell, 1978, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 7-10)
  - Abbreviated Transcripts of Letters Dated 1926 from Terrell, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Abbreviated Transcripts of Letters Dated from Terrell, 1978, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
  - Abbreviated Transcripts of Letters Dated 1929 from Terrell, 1978, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 14-17)
  - Abbreviated Transcripts of Letters Dated 1930 from Terrell, 1978, (5 folders) (Box 1, Folder 18-22)
  - Abbreviated Transcripts of Letters Dated 1931 from Terrell, 1978, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 23-26)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1924, June, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 27-28)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1924, July, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 29-32)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1924, August, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 33-35)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1924, September, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 36-39)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1924, October, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 40-41)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1924, November, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 42-44)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1924, December, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 45-48)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1925, January, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 49-51)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1925, February, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 52-54)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1925, March, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 55-58)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1925, April, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 59-62)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1925, May, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 63-65)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1925, June, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 66-68)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1925, July, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 69-72)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1925, August, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 73-76)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1925, September, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 77-80)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1925, October, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 81-84)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1925, November, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 85-88)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1925, December, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 89-92)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1926, January, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1926, February, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1926, March, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 7-9)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1926, April, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 10-12)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1926, May (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1926, July (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1928, July (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1928, August, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1928, September, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 18-20)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1928, October, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 21-23)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1928, November, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 24-27)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1928, December, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 28-31)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1929, January, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 32-35)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1929, February, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 36-39)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1929, March, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 40-43)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1929, April, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 44-47)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1929, May, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 48-51)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1929, June, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 52-55)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1929, July, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 56-58)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1929, August, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 59-62)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1929, September, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 63-66)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1929, October, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 67-70)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1929, November, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 71-74)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1929, December, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 75-77)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1930, January, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 78-80)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1930, February, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 81-83)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1930, March, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 84-87)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1930, April, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 88-91)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1930, May, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 92-95)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1930, June, (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1930, July, (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 5-8)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1930, August, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 9-11)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1930, September, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 12-14)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1930, October, (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 15-18)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1930, November, (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 19-22)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1930, December, (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 23-26)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1931, January, (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 27-30)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1931, February, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 31-33)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1931, March, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 34-36)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1931, April, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 37-39)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1931, May, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 40-42)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1931, June, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 43-45)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1931, July, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 46-48)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1931, August, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 49-51)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1931, September, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 52-53)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1933, January (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1933, June, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 55-56)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1933, July, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 57-58)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1933, August (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1933, September (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1933, October (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1933, November, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 62-63)
  - Letters from Terrell, 1933, December, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 64-65)
  - General Letters, undated, (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 66-69)
  - General Letters, 1908-1927 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - General Letters, 1928, (5 folders) (Box 3, Folder 71-75)
  - General Letters, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - General Letters, 1930, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 77-79)
  - General Letters, 1931, (6 folders) (Box 3, Folder 80-85)
  - General Letters, 1933-1934 (Box 3, Folder 86)
  - General Letters, 1937-1943 (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - General Letters, 1944-1956 (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - General Letters, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 89)
- Diaries, 1965-1978, Series 3:; (Boxes 3-4; 12 folders)
  Fourteen diaries describe Terrell's daily activities including several European trips.
  - Diaries, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - Diaries, 1967-1968, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 91-93)
  - Diaries, 1969-1970, (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Diaries, 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Diaries, 1973-1974, (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 4-6)
  - Diaries, 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Diaries, 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Financial Material, 1925-1933, Series 4:; (Box 4; 7 folders)
  Scattered financial material includes banking records, check registers, and miscellaneous receipts.
  - Banking Records, 1925-1930, (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 9-11)
  - Check Registers, 1928-1930, (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 12-13)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts, 1928-1933 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous Notes Concerning Finances, 1929, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Artwork, 1925-1982, Series 5:; (Boxes 4, 6; 7 folders)
  Artwork includes three sketchbooks containing several block prints, and miscellaneous sketches including portraits and anatomical studies.
  - Sketchbook 1, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Sketchbook 2, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Sketchbook 3, 1930-1934 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Portrait Sketches, 1974, undated, (see also Box 6) (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous Sketches, 1982, undated, (see also Box 6) (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Oversized Portrait Sketch, 1974 (Box 6 (sol))
  - Oversized Sketch of a Torso, 1982 (Box 6 (sol))
- Printed Material, 1911-1976, Series 6:; (Box 4; 15 folders)
  Printed material includes clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs for Terrell and for others, programs, and miscellaneous brochures for the purchase of artwork, art supplies, and hearing aids.
  - Clippings, undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Clippings, 1911 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Clippings, 1927-1943 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Clippings, 1944, (4 folders) (Box 4, Folder 24-27)
  - Clippings, 1945-1951 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Clippings, 1972-1974 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Terrell, 1944, undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Others, 1930-1945, undated (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Programs, 1945-1976 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Miscellaneous Brochures, undated (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Booklet "A Short Guide in Architecture, Painting, Sculpture and Landscape Architecture for Italy?," by the American Academy in Rome, 1916 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, undated (Box 4, Folder 35)
- Photographs, 1925-1972, Series 7:; (Box 5; 15 folders)
  Photographs are of Terrell, his colleagues, studio, and his artwork. Albums contain photographs of his apartment, the Riverhead studio, commissioned projects, and exhibition installations.
  - Photographs of Terrell, 1929, undated (Box 5 (pam), Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Terrell and Colleagues, 1970-1972 (Box 5 (pam), Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Terrell's Studio, 1927, undated (Box 5 (pam), Folder 3)
  - Photograph Album 1, 1932-1955, (3 folders) (Box 5 (pam), Folder 4-6)
  - Photograph Album 2, 1936-1970, (2 folders) (Box 5 (pam), Folder 7-8)
  - Photograph Album 3, 1939-1947, (4 folders) (Box 5 (pam), Folder 9-12)
  - Photograph of a Painting by Terrell, undated (Box 5 (pam), Folder 13)
  - Photographs of Sculpture by Terrell, 1925-1928, undated, (2 folders) (Box 5 (pam), Folder 14-15)